A Finding Aid to the Peter Blume Papers, 1870-2001, in the Archives of American Art aaa.blumpete
Archives of American Art
- Writings and Notes, 1929-1986; Series 3; 0.5 Linear feet Box 3, 9
  - Lists of Works of Art, circa 1969 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    Oversized material housed in Box 9, F2
  - "Peter Blume," by Robert Ulrich Godsoe, Mock-Up Biography, circa 1938 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - "Third Declamation," by Kenneth Burke, circa 1940 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Forward, by John Driscoll, for Metamorphosis Catalog, Ditenfass Gallery, circa 1940 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - "Grandma Moses and Peter Blume," by Eloise Barrangon, Poem, circa 1948 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - "The World," by Wade Van Done, Poem, circa 1950 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Poetry, by Heber Blankenhorn, circa 1960s (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - "Peter Blume," by Frank Getlein, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - "The Life and Works of Peter Blume," by George John Seidel, College of Wooster, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Poetry, by Nancy Cardozo, circa 1968 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Speech, by Gordon Hendricks, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Children's Criticism, on "The Rock", 1974 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - "Peter Blume's Ventriloquist Act," by Mark R. Kriss, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - "Peter Blume's Paintings of the 1930's [sic]," by Barbara D. Gallati, Thesis, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - "The Rock by Peter Blume" by Michael A. Kelly, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - "Peter Blume--Sixty Years of His Art (1926-1986)," by Frank Anderson Trapp with Forward by Malcolm Cowley, circa 1986 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Oversized Lists of Works of Art, scanned with Box 3, F20, circa 1970s (Box 9, Folder 2)
- Subject Files, circa 1930-1988; Series 4; 0.5 Linear feet Box 3-4
  Subject files were originally maintained by Peter Blume regarding organizations, works of art, exhibitions, reference files, and about Blume's brother-in-law, Heber Blankenhorn. Files include a variety of materials, such as correspondence, administrative records, writings, printed material, and photographs. Reference files contains photographs and clippings of works of art used as inspiration by Blume.
  - American Academy of Arts and Letters (Box 3)
    - Correspondence, Copies, 1973-1975 (Box 3, Folder 36)
    - Meeting Minutes, 1973-1975 (Box 3, Folder 37)
    - Meeting Minutes, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 38)
    - Reports, 1974-1976 (Box 3, Folder 39)
    - Treasurer's Reports, 1973-1974 (Box 3, Folder 40)
    - Statement of Income, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - American Artists Congress, 1930s (Box 3, Folder 42)
    Includes correspondence, writings, printed material, and administrative records
  - Autumn Silkscreen, 1987-1988 (Box 3, Folder 43)
    Includes a proposal, correspondence, and legal records
  - The Crucifixation, 1954-1955 (Box 3, Folder 44)
    Includes correspondence and printed material
  - Blankenhorn, Heber, 1931-1971 (Box 3, Folder 45)
    Includes material concerning Blankenhorn's donation of his personal papers and military career, and printed materials.
  - "Chicago Show" (1976)--Museum of Contemporary Art, 1975-1976 (Box 3, Folder 46)
    Includes correspondence, printed material, photographs, and lists of works of art
  - Connecticut Council on the Arts, 1979-1980 (Box 3, Folder 47)
    Includes writings, photographs, and printed material
  - Eternal City, 1937-1939 (Box 3, Folder 48-49)
  - Tasso's Oak, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 50)
    Includes correspondence, photographs, and printed material
  - Reference Files, circa 1930-circa 1960 (Box 3, Folder 51-55)
  - The Rock, 1948-1957 (Box 4, Folder 1-2)
    Includes clippings and material regarding the Carnegie Prize. Oversized material housed in Box 9, F4.
  - Oversized The Rock Clippings, scanned with Box 4, F1-2, 1948 (Box 9, Folder 4)
- Personal Business and Financial Records, 1934-1983; Series 5; 0.6 Linear feet Box 4, 9
  Found here are records relating to the sale, exhibition, and loan of Peter Blume's works of art. Also found are financial records relating to the construction of Blume's home.
  - Business Correspondence (Box 4)
    - The Boat, 1936-1946 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Coe Kerr Gallery, 1976-1984 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Currier Gallery of Art, 1963-1964 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Ditenfass Gallery, 1973-1990 (Box 4, Folder 6-7)
    - Durlacher Bros., 1941-1967 (Box 4, Folder 8-10)
    - Julian Levy Gallery, 1938-1944 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Kennedy Galleries, 1967-1968 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Kay Sage Tanguy Estate, 1963-1965 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Museum of Modern Art, 1934-1983 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Public Works of Art Project and Public Buildings Administration, 1934-1943 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - The Rock, 1952-1955 (Box 4, Folder 16)
      Regarding conservation and restoration
    - WPA, Cannonsburg, Pennsylvania Post Office, 1937 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Consignment Receipts and Lists, 1963-1971 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Sales Receipts, 1970-1971 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Gift Receipts, 1963 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Invoice, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Price Lists, circa 1960-1970 (Box 4, Folder 22-23)
  - Mailing List, circa 1970 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Legal Records, 1955 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Condition Reports, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Tax Correspondence, 1968 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Household and Building Records and Invoices, 1958-1972 (Box 4, Folder 28-30)
    Oversized material housed in Box 9, F3
  - Oversized Household and Building Records, scanned with Box 4, F28-30, 1958-1959 (Box 9, Folder 3)
- Printed Material, 1930-1990; Series 6; 0.7 Linear feet Box 4-5, 9, OV 15-16
  This series has been partially scanned. In some cases, only relevant pages of printed materials have been scanned.
  Printed materials concern Peter Blume's career, exhibitions, artwork, and art in general. Exhibition announcements and catalogs are found for Peter Blume's solo and group shows, some of which are annotated by Blume. Also found are posters, one of which includes a poem by Malcolm Cowley entitled Urn that is illustrated by Blume.
  - Auction Catalog, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Bulletins, 1934; 1984 (Box 4, Folder 32-33)
  - Clippings, 1930-1939 (Box 4, Folder 34-36)
  - Clippings, 1940-1949 (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - Clippings, 1950-1959 (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - Clippings, 1960-1969 (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - Clippings, 1970-1979 (Box 4, Folder 40)
  - Clippings, 1980-1989 (Box 4, Folder 41)
  - Clippings, 1990 (Box 4, Folder 42)
  - Clippings, circa 1930-circa 1980 (Box 4, Folder 43)
  - Clippings, Concerning Friends, 1938-circa 1980 (Box 4, Folder 44)
  - Congressional Record, Communist Activities in Museums, 1952 (Box 4, Folder 45)
  - Exhibition Announcements, 1964-1982 (Box 4, Folder 46)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1940-1985 (Box 4, Folder 47-49)
    Oversized material housed in Box 9, F5
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1948 (Box 4, Folder 50)
    Annotated
  - Magazines, 1924-1963 (Box 4, Folder 51-54)
  - Magazines, 1961-1988 (Box 5, Folder 1-5)
  - Reproductions of Works of Art, circa 1940; circa 1990 (Box 5, Folder 6-7)
    Oversized material housed in Box 9, F1
  - Horizon, 1961 July (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Oversized Reproductions of Works of Art, scanned with Box 5, F6-7, circa 1990 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Oversized Exhibition Catalog, scanned with Box 4, F47-49, 1940 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Posters, 1950s-1970s (Box OV 15, Folder 1)
  - Posters, 1950s-1970s (Box OV 16, Folder 1)
- Scrapbooks, 1934-1942; Series 7; 3 Folders Box 5
  Found is a clippings scrapbook dating from 1934 to 1939 and a fragment of a scrapbook from 1942 to 1944. The clippings scrapbook contains articles, most of which discuss Blume's works of art South of Scranton and The Eternal City. The scrapbook fragment contains a clipping, a postcard, a telegram from Ebie Blume to Mrs. Heber Blankenhorn, a diary entry, and a ledger page concerning the running of a household.
  - Scrapbook 1, 1934-1939 (Box 5, Folder 9-10)
  - Scrapbook 2, Fragment, 1942 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    Includes a clipping, telegram, diary, and page of a ledger
- Photographs, 1917-circa 1980; Series 8; 1.1 Linear feet Box 5-6, 9
  Found are portraits and snapshots of Peter Blume, Grace 'Ebie' Blume, family members, friends, and colleagues. Other photographs depict travel, parties, exhibitions, the outdoors, homes, pets, and of works of art including paintings and sculpture.
  Photographs of Peter Blume depict Blume painting outdoors and in his studio, with his art, with Grace Blume, and with family and friends. Travel photos are from Europe, Japan, and the American West. Some of the travel photos are of Ned and Nancy Holsten, the Blumes' travel companions and friends. Photographs of friends and family include the Cowleys, the Blankenhorns, the Askews, the Josephsons, and the Sobys, among others.
  Photographs from a terrace party, likely taken by H. Strauss, depict many of the Blumes' friends and family in addition to Arthur Miller.
  Photographs of exhibitions are from the American Institute in Rome and the Carnegie Institute.
  - Photo Album, 1953 (Box 5, Folder 12)
    Harry Blume's Birthday
  - Peter Blume, Portraits, circa 1930-circa 1970 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Peter Blume, Painting in Studio, 1944-circa 1960 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Peter Blume, Painting Outside, circa 1950 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Peter Blume, in Studio, circa 1950-circa 1970 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Peter Blume, With Art, circa 1960 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Peter Blume, Snapshots, circa 1925-circa 1970 (Box 5, Folder 18)
    Oversized material housed in Box 9, F8
  - Grace "Ebie" Blume, circa 1920-circa 1975 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Peter and Grace Blume, circa 1930-1965 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Peter and Family, circa 1935-1967 (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Peter, Grace, and Friends (Box 5)
    - Snapshots, circa 1920-circa 1960 (Box 5, Folder 22)
    - Trip to Woodlawn Plantation, circa 1950 (Box 5, Folder 23)
    - With Blankenhorns, circa 1945 (Box 5, Folder 24)
    - With Cowleys, 1945-circa 1970 (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Medal Presentation Ceremony, circa 1960 (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - Group Portrait, 1979 (Box 5, Folder 27)
    With Alfred Eisenstaedt, Raphael Soyer, Malcolm Cowley, Barbara Tuchman, and Peter Blume
  - Peter Blume with Georgia O'Keeffe, circa 1970 (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - Terrace and Pool Parties, circa 1950-1970 (Box 5, Folder 29-30)
    With Arthur Miller, Askews, Sobys, Josephsons, and Cowleys
  - Travel (Box 5)
    - Europe and Japan, circa 1950 (Box 5, Folder 31)
    - With Ned and Nancy Holsten, circa 1940s-1950s (Box 5, Folder 32-33)
    - American West, circa 1950 (Box 5, Folder 34)
  - Cowley Family, circa 1930-circa 1970 (Box 5, Folder 35)
  - Ann and Heber Blankenhorn, 1935-1952 (Box 5, Folder 36)
  - Friends and Family, 1917-1961 (Box 5, Folder 37)
    Mostly unidentified. Oversized material housed in Box 9, F9.
  - Pets and Animals, circa 1935 (Box 5, Folder 38)
  - Blume's Home, Gardens, and Construction, circa 1930s-1960s (Box 5, Folder 39)
  - Homes, Others, circa 1930 (Box 5, Folder 40)
  - Outdoors, Landscapes, circa 1940-circa 1950 (Box 5, Folder 41)
  - Exhibition, Carnegie and Others, 1982; 1934-1950 (Box 5, Folder 42)
  - Exhibition, American Academy in Rome, Venus (1974), circa 1974 (Box 5, Folder 43)
  - Contact Sheets, circa 1970 (Box 5, Folder 44)
  - Works of Art, Packets, circa 1970 (Box 5, Folder 45-49)
  - Works of Art, Sculpture, circa 1974 (Box 5, Folder 50)
    Oversized material housed in Box 9, F7
  - Works of Art, Studies, circa 1970 (Box 5, Folder 51)
  - Works of Art, Drawings, circa 1960 (Box 5, Folder 52)
  - Works of Art, Painting, circa 1960s (Box 5, Folder 53)
  - Works of Art, Painting, 1950s-1970s (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Transparencies, 1960s (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Slides, circa 1960 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Xeroxes of Photos of Works of Art, circa 1980 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Oversized Photos of Works of Art, Sculpture, scanned with Box 5, F50, circa 1970 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Oversized Peter Blume, Snapshot, scanned with Box 5, F18, circa 1980 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Oversized Friends and Family Photos, scanned with Box 5, F37, circa 1960s (Box 9, Folder 9)
- Artwork, 1932-1984; Series 9; 2 Linear feet Box 6-9, OV 10-14
  Works of art by Blume include sketches, preliminary drawings, prints, and one final drawing. Media include pencil, pen, pastel, and charcoal. Sketches entitled Doodles were likely numbered and identified by Blume. Also found are a series of drawings of heads, some of which are mounted. Studies for Blume's works include: Parade (1930), The Obelisk (1932), Harps (1932), Fracture Ward (1945), The Rock (1948), The Shrine (1950), The Crucifixion (1951), Castle of Euralyus (1952), Landscape in Bali (1954), The Passage to Aetna (1956), Hadrian's Villa (1958), Tasso's Oak (1960), Banyon Trees (1961), Winter (1964), Summer (1966), Satyr with Cock (1967), Recollection of the Flood (1969), Boulders of Avila (1976), From the Metamorphosis (1979), Crashing Surf (1982), and Autumn (1984).
  Works by Peter Blume owned by the Craton family are also found. These include three prints, one entitled Harps, and one drawing entitled New England Snow, which was exhibited at the Whitney Museum of American Art in 1938.
  Also found is a work by Deborah Nourse Lattimore entitled Gilt Venus.
  - Designs for a Stand, circa 1960 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Doodles, DDOND 12-17, circa 1940s-circa 1970s (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Doodles, DDOND 18-25, circa 1940s-circa 1970s (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Doodles, DDOND 26-31, circa 1940s-circa 1970s (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Doodles, DDOND 32-50, circa 1940s-circa 1970s (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Doodles, DDOND 51-65, circa 1940s-circa 1970s (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Doodles, DDOND 66-89, circa 1940-circa 1970 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Doodles, DDOND 90-99, circa 1940s-circa 1970s (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Doodles, DDOND 100-113, circa 1940s-circa 1970s (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Doodles, DDOND 114-135, circa 1940s-circa 1970s (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Doodles, DDOND 136-154, circa 1940s-circa 1970s (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Doodles, DDOND 155-179 (174 missing), circa 1940s-circa 1970s (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Doodles, DDOND 180-197, circa 1940s-circa 1970s (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Doodles, DDOND 198-203, circa 1940-circa 1970 (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Doodles, DDOND 204-209 (and others), circa 1940s-circa 1970s (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - Doodles, DDOND 210-213, circa 1940s-circa 1970s (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - Sketches, 1944-1982 (Box 6, Folder 21-23)
  - Sketches, Heads, 1948-1975 (Box 6, Folder 24-28)
    Oversized material housed in Box 9, F6
  - Gilt Venus, by Deborah Nourse Lattimore, 1979 (Box 6, Folder 29)
    Oversized material housed in Box 9, F10
  - Prints and Drawings, Owned by Craton Family, 1936-1942 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Studies (Box 8)
    - Summer, 1960s (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Hadrian's Villa, circa 1958 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Fracture Ward, circa 1945 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Harps, 1932 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Obelisk, 1932 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Boulders of Avila, 1976 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Banyan Trees, 1961 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Landscape in Bali, 1954 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Passage to Etna, circa 1956 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - Castle of Euralus, 1952 (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - The Crucifixion and The Shrine, 1951-1952 (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - Winter, 1964 (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - Crashing Surf, Metamorphosis, Autumn, and Satyr with Cock, 1974-1984 (Box 8, Folder 13)
      Oversized material housed in OV 10.
    - Parade, Recollection of the Flood, Tasso's Oak, and The Rock, 1930-1969 (Box 8, Folder 14)
      Oversized material housed in OV 11 and OV 14.
    - Doodles, 1950s-1960s (Box 8, Folder 15-16)
  - Oversized Sketches of Heads scanned with Box 6, F24-28, 1950s-1969 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Oversized Artwork by Others scanned with Box 6, F29 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Oversized Studies of Crashing Surf, Metamorphosis, Autumn, and Satyr with Cock scanned with Box 8, Folder 13, 1984 (Box OV 10, Folder 1)
  - Oversized Studies of Recollection of the Flood and Tasso's Oak scanned with Box 8, Folder 14, 1969 (Box OV 11, Folder 1)
  - Oversized Studies of The Rock scanned with Box 8, Folder 14, circa 1950 (Box OV 14, Folder 1)
    Includes The Rock
  - Oversized Mounted Sketches, Untitled, 1950s-1960s (Box OV 12, Folder 1)
  - Oversized Mounted Sketches, Untitled, 1950s-1960s (Box OV 13, Folder 1)
- Craton Family Papers, 1870-2001; Series 10; 0.2 Linear feet Box 6
  This bulk of this series has been scanned; financial records have not been scanned.
  Found are family papers from Grace Blume's brother, James Craton and his wife, Catherine Sears Craton. The bulk of this series relates to the genealogical research performed by Catherine Craton on the Craton and Sears families. These materials include birth, marriage, military, baptismal, and death records, clippings, correspondence, and photographs. Also found is a letter from Grace Blume and an unsigned writing about Peter and Grace Blume by one of their nieces or nephews.
  - Certificates, Birth and Death, 1920-1976 (Box 6, Folder 30)
  - Certificates, Marriage, 1959-1974 (Box 6, Folder 31)
  - Burial Records, 1936-1974 (Box 6, Folder 32)
  - Baptismal Records, 1937-1949 (Box 6, Folder 33)
  - Wedding Invitation, 1919 (Box 6, Folder 34)
  - Military Records, Marshall Craton, circa 1970s (Box 6, Folder 35)
    Xerox copies of Marshall Craton's Civil War service records including correspondence, payroll and muster rolls. Date determined from the date of the copies.
  - Military Records, James Craton, 1917-1919 (Box 6, Folder 36)
  - Correspondence, James and Catherine Craton, 1941-1942 (Box 6, Folder 37)
  - Correspondence, Regarding Genealogy, 1936-1976 (Box 6, Folder 38)
  - Lists of Family Members, circa 1940 (Box 6, Folder 39)
  - Instructions for Family Cabin, 2001; 1945 (Box 6, Folder 41)
  - Financial and Tax Records, 1936-1956 (Box 6, Folder 42)
  - Clippings, 1911; 1974-1976 (Box 6, Folder 43)
  - Family Photographs, 1870-circa 1940 (Box 6, Folder 44)
  - Photocopies, Genealogical Material, circa 1970s (Box 6, Folder 45)